Ed Benguiat collection
Rochester Institute of Technology
Ed Benguiat collection
1953 - 2001
The Ed Benguiat Collection contains original sketches, phototypesetting materials such as photographic prints and negatives, and printed materials relating to the design, production, and promotion of typefaces generated or accumulated during the life and career of type designer, Ed Benguiat. The collection contains objects dating from 1953 to 2001. The collection is organized into two series: I. Graphic Work, and II. Typefaces. The first series contains printed and design work for logos and newspapers, promotional materials such as posters and booklets, or in-progress work such as sketches and paste-ups. The second series contains materials related to the designing and production of specific typefaces, predominately photographic negatives and transparencies, paste-ups, and type specimens.
33 Linear Feet
Benguiat, Ed
Cary Graphic Arts Collection Graphic Design Archive
Collection is organized into two series: I. Graphic Work (circa 1953 - 1990); II. Typefaces (circa 1960 - 2001). The collection is arranged first by genre, typeface alphabetically, by type style and weight, and then medium.
"Edward Benguiat. Biography of Ed Benguiat. Written by Elisa Halperin: Art Directors Club, 2000.
"Edward Ephram Benguiat. List of Benguiat's typefaces. Klingspor Museum, 2008.
Portions of this collection may not be reproduced. Please consult the curator.
Ephram Edward Benguiat was born in Brooklyn, New York, on October 27th, 1927. After serving time in the Air Corps during World War II, he returned home to New York and became an established jazz percussionist. He soon enrolled at the Workshop School of Advertising Art in New York City under Paul Standard, where he studied layout, design, typography, and calligraphy. In 1953, he became the associate director of Esquire magazine, whose logo he designed. In 1962 he met Ed Rondthaler, and joined Photo-Lettering, Inc. as their Typographic Design Director. During his time at Photo-Lettering, he also acted as editor of their promotional publication, PLINC, and produced over 400 typefaces for the phototypesetting firm. In 1971, Rondthaler, along with Herb Lubalin and Aaron Burns, founded the International Typeface Corporation, and contracted Benguiat for their first typeface—Souvenir. Benguiat and Lubalin partnered to develop ITC’s magazine, U&lc, and continued to produce new typefaces to add to the ITC repertoire. Benguiat served as vice president of ITC until 1986.
Ed Benguiat has designed over 600 typefaces including Bookman, Benguiat, Benguiat Gothic, Panache, Tiffany, Barcelona, handtooled versions of Century, Cheltenham, and Garamond, and the logotypes for brands and publications including The New York Times, Coca-cola, Playboy, Reader’s Digest, Sports Illustrated, Photoplay, and Look magazine. He has served as president of the Type Directors Club, and was awarded their TDC Medal in 1989. Benguiat is also a member of the Alliance Graphique Internationale. He later taught at The School of Visual Arts in New York, where he was awarded Teacher of the Year in 1995.
Carnase, Tom; Lubalin, Herb; Burns, Aaron; Caruso, Victor; Rondthaler, Edward; Paste-up (printing); mechanicals (camera-ready copy); typefaces (type forms); type specimens (documents); Type Directors Club of New York; Field and Stream; McCall's magazine; Look magazine; Museum of Television and Radio (New York, N.Y.); New York Times; Photo-Lettering Inc; Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts; International Typeface Corporation; Esquire, inc; negatives (photographs); script (typeface group); black-and-white prints (prints on paper); lithographs; Publications; Type and type-founding; Magazine covers -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Newspapers; Design; Graphic design; Logos (Symbols) -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Type designers; Graphic designers -- United States; Type and type-founding -- Design.; Roman type -- Specimens; Script type -- Specimens; Advertising; Graphic design -- 1950-1980; Typographers; black-and-white transparencies; sketches; logos; logotypes; typography; Phototypesetting; Type and type-founding -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Photostat; Drawings
The Ed Benguiat Collection contains design and development work on typefaces designed by Benguiat, as well as logos for clients, ranging from 1953 to 2001. Materials include original sketches for type and logo design; large sheet negatives, transparencies, and paste-ups for published and unpublished typefaces; type specimen catalogues and posters; and negatives and mock-ups for logos and newspapers, including The New York Times. Material pertains to Benguiat and his affiliated businesses, namely International Typeface Corporation and Photo-Lettering, Incorporated, with some work produced for the Type Directors Club. Predominate holdings include: ITC Barcelona, ITC Benguiat, ITC Bookman, and ITC Edwardian.
- Graphic Work, 1948 - 1995
  - Graphic Pieces, 1948 - 1994
    - Borders, 1955 - 1995
      - Border Negatives, 1955 - 1995
      - Border Prints, 1955 - 1995
    - Magazine cover mockups; Field & Stream, Look, and McCall's, 1958 - 1989
    - PLINC Famous Type Designer Sketches & Benguiat Quote Poster, undated
    - Publications: Other Side of the Coin Pamphlet, PLINC: A Typographic Journey, 1970 - 1990
    - Serif Structures & Serif Alphabet, undated
  - Logos, 1948 - 2001
    - Barcelona Olympics '92, negatives and pasteups, 1982 - 1992
    - Letterform Anatomy Poster Lithograph & Negatives, undated
    - Lincoln Center Logo, 1991 - 2001
      - Lincoln Center Logo Concept Drawings, 1996 - 2006
      - Lincoln Center Logo Negatives, 2001
      - Lincoln Center Logo Prints, 2001
    - Logo process work, 1948 - 2001
      - Logo Negatives; Alphabets & Images, Benguiat consultation advertisement, Cliff Freeman and Partners, Forbes, ITC clock logo, Lincoln Park Aviation, McCall’s, MR&T, PLINC, Type Directors Club, Village East/West, 1955 - 1990
      - Logos Prints; Esquire, McCall's, New York Orient Express, TGI logo bag, and Miscellaneous, 1948 - 1995
      - Logo Sketches; 21,Cooper Union, Eileen Hedy Shultz, Peter Cooper, PL&H, 1948 - 1995
  - Newspapers, 1961 - 1989
    - Newspaper Masthead Negatives; The New York Times, Star Ledger, 1961 - 1994
    - Newspaper Masthead Sketches, Layouts; The New York Times, Star Ledger, 1961 - 1994
- Typefaces, 1955 - 2001
  - Typeface Designs, 1955 - 1999
    - ITC American Typewriter, 1984 - 1994
    - ITC Barcelona, 1976 - 1986
      ITC Barcelona Roman Negatives
      ITC Barcelona Italics Negatives
      ITC Barcelona Paste-Ups
      ITC Barcelona Sketches
    - ITC Benguiat, 1973 - 1983
      ITC Benguiat Regular & Light, Roman & Italics Negatives
      ITC Benguiat Book, Roman & Italics Negatives
      ITC Benguiat Book Condensed, Roman & Italics Negatives
      ITC Benguiat Medium, Roman & Italics Negatives
      ITC Benguiat Medium Condensed, Roman & Italics Negatives
      ITC Benguiat Bold, Roman & Italics Negatives
      ITC Benguiat Bold Condensed, Roman & Italics Negatives
      ITC Benguiat Paste-Ups
    - ITC Benguiat Gothic, 1974 - 1984
      ITC Benguiat Gothic Book & Light Negatives
      ITC Benguiat Gothic Paste-Ups
      ITC Benguiat Gothic Type Specimens
    - ITC Bentley, 1984
      ITC Bentley Negatives & Transparencies
      ITC Bentley Type Specimens
    - ITC Bookman, 1970 - 1980
      ITC Bookman Negatives
      ITC Bookman Light, Roman & Italics Negatives
      ITC Bookman Demi & Medium, Roman & Italics Negatives
      ITC Bookman Bold, Roman & Italics Negatives
      ITC Bookman Outline & Contour, Negatives
      ITC Bookman Outline & Contour, Paste-Ups
    - Catalana, 1965 - 1995
      Catalana Book, Roman & Italics Negatives
      Catalana Bold, Roman & Italics, Second Weight Negatives
      Catalana Black, Roman & Italics Negatives
      Catalana Miscellanous Negatives
      Catalana Type Specimens
    - ITC Century Hand-Tooled Masters, Roman & Italics Negatives, 1988 - 1995
    - ITC Cheltenham Hand-Tooled Masters, Roman & Heavy Italics Negatives, 1988 - 1995
    - Congressional, 1955 - 1995
      Congressional First Weight Condensed Negatives
      Congressional First Weight Heavy Thins Condensed Negatives
      Congressional Second Weight Heavy Thins Negatives
    - ITC Edwardian Script, 1989 - 1999
      ITC Edwardian Regular Negatives
      ITC Edwardian Regular Ball Negatives
      ITC Edwardian Light & Heavy Simple Negatives
      ITC Edwardian Heavy Negatives
      ITC Edwardian Heavy Ball Negatives
      ITC Edwardian, Miscellaneous Single Character Negatives
      Edwardian script sketches & photocopies, circa 1994, 1989 - 1999
    - Egizanu Negatives & Type Specimens, 1982 - 1992
    - ITC Garamond Hand-Tooled Masters, Roman & Bold Italics Negatives, 1988 - 1995
    - Jackson, undated
      Jackson Negatives
      Jackson Sketches
    - ITC Modern No. 216, 1977 - 1987
      ITC Modern No. 216 Negatives
      ITC Modern No. 216 Type Specimens
    - ITC Panache, 1983 - 1993
      ITC Panache Negatives
      ITC Panache Book, Roman & Italics Negatives
      ITC Panache Heavy, Roman & Italics Negatives
      ITC Panache Italic Masters Negatives
      ITC Panache Type Specimens
    - Presidential, 1960 - 1990
      Presidential First Weight Hairline Thins Negatives
      Presidential First Weight Heavy Thins Negatives
      Presidential Second Weight Hairline Thins Negatives
      Presidential Second Weight Heavy Thins Negatives
      Presidential Second Weight Condensed Negatives
      Presidential Third Weight Hairline Thins Negatives
      Presidential Third Weight Heavy Thins Negatives
    - Souvenir Unpublished Weight Sketches, 1965 - 1975
    - Spectra, ITC Tiffany, Miscellaneous Types, Negatives, circa 1974
    - Spencerian Original Drawings, undated
  - Type Specimens, 1964 - 1988
- Ed Benguiat signed T-Square, 1960